you look great
Thanks yeah slight slightly unshaved and
sexy how's your summer speed fantastic
um we had we had a ball at the board
landing it was amazing
communities really working and I think
it pulled off the best run in Europe
this year and yeah but in general I mean
Peter nice for a military oath to each
other at the borderland the last night
well if two straight guys are gonna get
married
mm-hmm unless you want to make a big
sensation out of Sweden becoming the
first country where they've gone full
circle and straight men are not marrying
each other if you go back to the history
of marriage you will discover that
marriage didn't start with man and woman
marriage started with men marrying each
other for military service
as a military oath and that oath
eventually when he was tied to property
became the way you married clowns
together which is what marriage Saoirse
yes it's new try I've been married the
clan with another clan so that's a what
that's about like 5000 years ago or
something like that the military older
than that way older than that so we just
decided to go back to the original
marriages of the militarism and swear
the military Charlie cool
based on tapes in in Greece before the
Spartans the the guys in Greece who
really reinvented the military oath with
oath II be ins oh yeah so you have a
girlfriend and a husband or hospice the
wrong husband's not the right word I
didn't think so I've got a life brother
who I live with and I got a life sister
I do not live with other women okay
those are my primary relationships we're
already going aren't we yeah I just
pressed record right away this time
because I didn't know I thought
something interesting would just pop up
that we might miss I've been I've been
studying the Kushan Empire quite a lot
recently I find it incredibly
interesting and
and I think a reason why we have
underrated the Kushan Empire in Europe
is because this was of course the Golden
Age of the Roman Empire so you know
about a hundred years before Christ
until what three or four hundred years
later the Cutrone's had invaded from
Central Asia and occupied northern India
it was the only empire that actually
encapsulated both of India and most of
Persia any incredibly Golden Age for
Buddhism and Zoroastrianism met both
state religions within the cushion
Empire and obviously what we talked
about before you and I about the silk
trade triad was really established this
sort of fruitful relationship between
Taoism and Buddhism and so Astor's must
in between the person the Chinese and
the Indian religions and of course
Tibetan Buddhism the you a narrative
there's a salt of these marriages so you
know people traveled I mean they were
nomadic and it says people came from
Mongolia peacefully all the way down to
India and integrated with the Indians
during this time and then spread of
course Buddhism the other way eventually
Hinduism took back anymore but Buddhism
on the other hand was spread along the
Silk Road over the rest of Asia and it
intermarried with Zoroastrianism and I
think an important thing we need to
start studying there's some scholars
some Asian scholars working in America
they started studying if this could also
possibly be the route of Sufism now of
course this is a really really touchy
subject because awesomes cannot make up
the mind what they want include Sufism
or not this versus one includes Sufism
in Islam when it pays off well I know
Sufis that say that Sufism is pre Muslim
it is absolutely yes it is absolutely
and there seems to be two different
schools that could both turn out to be
right there's a Kurdish school it seems
to locate the origin of Sufism in
Mesopotamia which is of course person
before the Arabs invaded I mean the
Persian Empire did the capital was Tessa
form which is basically now a server
suburb of Baghdad
so the original bag that is Persian so
so the person's bill
Baghdad or Stephon it's called which is
the capital of the Persian Empire this
desert was then fighting
be songs which ironically been the
capital of Roman Empire the Roman Empire
moved its capital to the east away from
Rome to Constantinople or basalts and
the Persian capital moved from central
Persia and Persepolis onto steady form
which is contemporary Baghdad and then
became to connect with the personal and
the Persian Empire the Roman Emperor
basically you know were the two major
empires and this was a struggle between
Christianity and so astron ISM while
there was still at least Christianity
was still being formed and was still
under a lot of influence and this war
exhausted both Pershing Roman it
exhausted boast as if on Amazon's and it
did so most of all because of a huge
plague that hit Europe in the 6th
century there were two major plates the
first one was in the 6th century and the
second one the one we usually hear about
it so in the 14th century and the most
devastated the Middle East and the
devastated Europe but the plague in the
6th century evaporated you know but
somewhere between the third or half of
the Middle East population was wiped out
the Persian Empire basically went
bankrupt because of the plague
so ostensive own ambitions were still
fighting each other this opened up the
entire Middle East for just about
anybody what years are we talking about
here no 7 century are we still in the
7th century ok this is everything so the
6th century East when the playhead the
seventies when you had the devastating
results of a major plague in the Middle
East in Europe the Middle East was even
more weakened than Europe was so so this
weekend especially for the person Empire
was even more weakened this is the end
of the Sassanid Empire
so the Sassanid Empire certainly there
was a little innovation coming from the
south from places called Mecca and
Medina we all know this is the Muslim
Arab invasion the massive animation was
probably the fastest military expansion
over history we should remember Mohammed
not all as a founder of the religion but
more than anything is one of the big
military geniuses of history and he
basically conquered about half the known
world you know they went all the way up
to way into Siberia conquered half
Russia concreting of western China and
they were in India certainly with
mobiles later in the conquered all of
the Middle East and they took North
Africa from the Christians but they took
the entire person Empire from the
Persians the Persian Emperor even
escaped China you know except escaped
exam which was the biggest city in the
world at the time cm was the the
starting point of the Silk Road in the
Chinese side and Cairo was of course the
other and no imitation of the determined
homeland station of this is growing the
other side in Cairo in Egypt
accion were the two biggest cities of
the world closely followed by Baghdad
and Damascus and of course the other
major cities like nerve and summer
economy had a big trading post along the
super six are the seven biggest cities
of the world were probably along the
Silk Route we come to the end of the
thirteenth century so but before that if
you go back to the seventh century this
leads to the Muslim Arab invasion and of
course the Muslims invade a way more
than they had expected
basically Mohammed had set out to Crane
something like to pop version of
Christianity for Arabs like a very
simplified religion moots make it easy
let's build a mosque that looks like a
mamela a breast let's build a minaret
and it looks like it follows a dick
let's make it a very Freudian and simple
and let's build mosques and minarets
next to each other and have only one
gone call this God Allah and basically
this is God and Satan and everything
thrown into one and you've got the
character or not it's kind of genius to
make such a simple religion the problem
is of course that this religion was
militarily successful but could never be
kept together didn't have a theological
center of any kind it's and still today
you saw his cursed mic decentralized and
it was divided against itself since the
beginning they've been fighting each
other and you think of a men function
like when men are wasted like a large
groups of men if they can't have a
theory that they agree on and a symbol
or the theory which is a high priest
they will instead go for a lineage
that's exactly
religious books are full of well he did
some he'd give birth to him and he gave
birth to him and he could birth to have
a nikkie birthing there's a long long
long long images you know to impress on
women or impress on each other whatever
and that's essentially song still today
the conflict between Shia and Sunni is
not a theological one as you would
expect between capitalism and
Protestantism an Orthodox and
Christianity know the conflict is still
wanna finish like if it is that the guy
who marry into the family or is it the
you know the grandson who should be in
charge of things and still today that's
she also what's interesting
like you you and I are both interested
in Tantra and
I remember going to the Ghibli Museum in
Paris I'm seeing like before and after
the Islamic invasions and there was all
his time tantric iconography all over
the world like it wasn't just in India
or Tibet it was goes all the way you
know all over the world then it kind of
disappeared after the point being it's
not surgery yeah exactly
point being that cirrhosis should never
be mistaken for being some kind of promo
Abrahamic religion the less impotence or
ask you to submit and the Abrahamic
religions is virtually zilch
but the credibility of Surat Annisa says
it was a stage leader the Persian Empire
was the Muslims wanted to claim its
arrest and was a religion of the books
it was like they considered it like a
very complex formal religion prior to
song and mostly Islam is resting tonight
a very peaceful relationship today but
this is dead wrong because this the
historical connection so a sternness
must make peace with Buddhism and it is
with now ISM and it's with the Eastern
traditions definitely Eastern religion
and the way you see it is that the
Mobile's in the Persian Empire say the
Sassanid Empire that's like from about
the birth of Christ
up until the seventh century in the
animation this is the Sassanid Empire it
was just as important as the Roman
Empire it was centered on Persepolis and
eventually they move the capital to
Stefan which is like currency Baghdad
and and this was the center of the
person Empire in so rasterizer was the
state religion and they considered
anybody was agnostic or anybody was a
dualist of any kind
many kills because they don't be
heretics and they will execute we're
after the mercilessly because harassed
anism is fundamentally a modest religion
exactly like buddhism and taoism so if
it's a Manas religion it has nothing to
do with do this of me so I'm a
Christianity that are all dualist
religions this is fundamental to the
shift and the difference between West
and East when we discuss west and east
historically dualism and monism unless
your separation between is the
separation we don't have a single trace
of monism before Thomas Akina starts
playing around with it in Europe and
then eventually that leads to Spinoza
who's the first openly modest
philosopher in the West if the Nosa was
cursed by the Jews he was cursed by the
Christians they consider us to be this
horrible infidel I mean he came along
with his ideas that he'd gotten from who
Sufi mystics in Spain and Portugal you
were killed in Europe if you were a
modest hmm you were persecuted and
killed you were persecuted and killed in
the Islamic world if you've Romanus
unless you were a Sufi so this is the
origin of Sufism so we have Sufism
definitely to thank for Spinoza zhim so
the arrival of modest thinking that
comes of course under the umbrella
philosophy not theology although Spinoza
claimed to be a theologian another
philosopher we gladly placed him in a
new camp that we called philosophy and
in the world of philosophy from the 16th
century forward in the West you could
think all kinds of weird and wicked and
strange ideas without getting executed
because you are a person philosopher
this is a whole new academic discipline
so you took it out of theology because
if you stayed with in theology plague
thinks it's a Catholic Church or at
least Luther did not agree with you had
your head chopped off okay but if you
left theology and had no claims to the
fortune of the church you could be
philosopher you could think more freely
but even with Spinoza it was his friend
the cart alignments realized his genius
and they were all you know
contemporaries they defended his right
to speak his mind
so philosophers started speaking them
you know for each other like no no no
wait a second I'm the car to have these
ideas I'm a duelist I don't want to
break with Christianity because I'm
actually dualist and actually he took
dualism to a whole new level I mean if
anybody took dualism seriously it was
the card so we the modern dualism we
have in the West we inherited from a
current and that's why I talk about
Cartesian individualism and I call talk
about Cartesian dualism of time but
Spinoza introduced monism and in a weird
way so did Lyman its except that he
didn't really understand probably that's
what he did
Linus has been also much closer to each
other and you have to read them next to
each other now when you study them but I
find it interesting that the kickstart
in the West for a - tradition starting
with Spinoza been being fulfilled by
Hegel cetera starts with su v--'s you
could not have Spinoza unless his family
had Portuguese Jewish origins in a
billion Jews often accepted Sufi mystics
and found them interesting and when the
Jewish tradition you could of course be
a mystic and as a mystic you could have
sperm on ISM and you could you know
think of your whole vows maybe being the
universe or something you could
definitely do with a law at least if you
were a Sufi so we have to go back now
and trace the origins of Sufism and I
find incredibly interesting that we
explore one I talked about it I talked
about the Kurdish explanation which is
no this started out in the bazaars or
Basra and bonded so when Islam took over
and Baghdad now became the new capital
of the Arab world basically they just
took over stessa phone from from the
person's and said you know a few miles
west of stessa phone we build a new
capital on the tigress and we call it
back you already had the masks as you
were at Cairo so then you have three
major huge urban centers in his family
world and that led him to the Islamic
Golden Age what he sent essentially the
Egyptians and the Babylonians and the
Mesopotamians and the Persians created
the culture the Arabs claimed were there
was there so this is the Muslim Golden
Age so but I finally interesting so they
said you claim that the Kurdish
tradition could be the origin of Sufism
the other claim
is that it started in Central Asia
you're out of your suit isn't right the
local Kurdish religion that's non-muslim
does it isn't really it's a folk version
of Zoroastrianism and they are
collaborating now so rest em ISM has
been declared an official religion in
neurotic Lorestan and of course a lot of
Kurds are not that happy about being
Muslims any longer after having being
raped and pillaged by the Islamic state
so there's a lot of conversions going on
now in Iraq and Kurdistan in the convert
to the reston ISM and they can also keep
the UCD practices because that's just
considered the focus or s tourism so it
is our master
it is Zoroastrianism all around and this
again why can't you grow tourism is the
connection between the two is that we
don't see a single single example of
conflict between Zoroastrians and
buddhists until this day to me the yin
and yang they just are just like so
closely connected but they're just two
different radically different sides of
the same coin so to me Zoroastrianism
it's the phallic version of an religion
where the magical version of that
religion is Buddhism and it's more like
you and me it's a it's a matter of taste
why do you want to call yourself a
Buddhist or as arrest you mm-hmm
actually complement each other perfectly
Taoism you've tried to unify the two
into one religion but this is something
brilliant about actually keeping two
religions separate within the same
Empire it can actually more fruitful and
I think that's exactly what they did in
the Kushan Empire the cushions came from
Central Asia what is it can I ask you
question before you going off the story
wait why do you think why do you think
the asterism is phallic and Buddhism is
make sure our color perhaps tourism is
all about linear history it's all about
we started here and we're gonna build an
amazing glorious future up there on the
hill so we're gonna take humanity and
build a civilization and we're gonna
shut ourselves in the world by creating
an amazing future together
completely finally and it's not about
having been in a paradise that we fan
out of and we're gonna try to restore
which is the judeo-christian tradition
oh if you're gonna separate spirit and
body
you better have a place where they were
united in the beginning then separated
then the body became dirty and sinful
and sex you must hate it and all the
shit that goes to judeo-christian
religion I'm with the song and then one
day maybe the Savior will come and save
us and bring back the paradise that that
is the that is the trajectory of
judeo-christian Islamic religion of
Abrahamic religion with the Restless of
there is no such starting point there
was no paradise there was the original
tribe it wasn't a manic and the nomadic
life they became settled and the
difficult of the shift from the nomadic
to the settled is what Zoroaster is
concerned with when he formulates his
religion three thousand seven hundred
years ago and this is a religion of
process and change it's an ever changing
ever a fresh religion that is not
believe in perfection
the police in wholeness she believes in
completion of their life and it does not
build pyramids which Egyptians did which
then inspired their Arbor hammocks to do
the same
no they just throw away the bodies in
nature when somebody died something the
Tibetans later caught it and took him
from Zoroastrianism they did you throw
with anybody somebody's that because
they're dead they're over they lived
their whole for life and it's time to go
to the next generation and keep building
the civilization nothing can be more
funny than that the phallic is the
longing to transcend who you are and the
generation you belong to and create
something better and higher than what we
currently have this urge is the phallic
and that explore the forest is invented
the first Messiah so the Messiah vaduz
later copied for the nation of Israel
was a universal Messiah which is why I
said a Christian I'm not digging into
this concept the name for that is the
associate so the so Sheehan is a concept
that was invented three thousand seven
hundred oh by so roster located
somewhere in contemporary US Pakistan
which was porous on a Persian Kingdom at
the time and in Khorasan so as to
declared his new religion and the new
religion was phallic and he declared
we're gonna build a better higher world
by adding more complexity and being able
to handle that complex
he mortis kick-started the
Revolutionists then started with written
language the higher complexity level
would enable us to create more complex
and therefore better society that's what
we call civilization today civilization
isn't starts with raster and the
interesting thing is he was not a
plagiarist
he did not believe it was a perfect
world we should imitate to try to grade
No
he believed the world was ever-changing
and he called this concept of Itachi
we strive towards wholeness in our own
lives too one day I pass on the world to
somebody who can then improve on it
mmm-hmm that is phallic and this is what
the Sochi aren't is part of the
mythology so you know the thousand-year
rice we should take back that term from
Hitler because it was a mental Azure
roster but the the end of Anna poke at
the end of a thousand-year Empire when
things fell apart
decadence set in the cell shampooed
common saints and of course that's for a
Judaic as well as there's a copy d
totally from the person's it wasn't
Babylon if they copied the concept of
the Messiah
so the Messiah and idea the Jewish
people yeah the nation of Israel have
their own Savior that would come and
save them and of course King David was
the first one who was a messiah
you know they made up Moses before King
David as an historical figure he never
existed but Moses of course another
Messiah so these are leaders but but for
the Persians it was important whereas
Israel to me is the name of the perfect
nation the name of the perfect Empire is
personal and in what the person's then
inspire us to do today is to recreate
that into the universal environment that
we somehow have to create to save the
planet today so we have to go back to
these traditions we have to dig into
this and what I find encouraging is that
we're gonna give the Muslim sorrow if
they go with Sufism because we see this
with in Sufism
the you and I can find something that
aligns with your Buddhism in my
Zoroaster oh sure
sufism can be so many weird things
terrible things origin is so important I
always go to a team ology when I use
words I always tell people that if
there's several different
interpretations of a term then you know
don't believe the last American
best-selling writer that's the best
interpret no go to the origin of the
word etymology and study word and then
claim it again so the same thing here we
should really try to find the original
sufism which definite is pre-islamic
there's an enormous Buddhist influence
in Sufism there's definitely an enormous
Lauriston influence I would say it's a
confluence I would say the kushan empire
plays an absolutely key earlier all the
scholars have talked to claim the same
thing the cushion empire with Central
Asians who walked all the way down to
northern India and established an empire
for 400 years that also included some
backed out the entire Silk Road was
controlled by the cushions meaning there
was a flow a constant flow trade and
information and knowledge from China
through Central Asia down to person
engineer so this was a golden age for
culture why we know so little of it is
because we number one neglected and
number two the Mongol invasion destroyed
most most of the manuscripts of that
theory so we need to go care for me
forward and try to use whatever means we
can have to start a nice historical
period because I think for you as a
Tibetan Buddhist for for Buddhism in
general I'm not a Tibetan Buddhist I
don't if you are not to them no no not I
don't attach Tibetan to it I'm a
violinist oh nothing to do with Tibetan
like my teachers American I the
practices I do are English no defense I
accept them yeah at all dogs and I'm not
I'm not I'm not obsessed with Tibetan
culture I don't work to get in clothes
I'm ready to Tibetan finish you know is
kind of ugly you know and I'm not very
person I've had quite a few person
dinners in my life
you know I believe sir Aston ISM is
still is the only properly universal
religion possibly combining the Buddhism
and I think that that connection there's
a rastan Buddhist connection he's the
best narrative we have today going
forward by the way we got to talk about
for Vaculik is going to talk about him
today another Buddhist thing well I was
laughing a bit earlier because I was
struck by the by the contrast between
your your grand narratives your dramatic
grand narratives and this sort of subtle
psychological psychologizing that
happens on the American continent yeah
you know what I think of psychology
the problem with psychologists or
psychiatry it's an American innovation
and whenever I talk to the American who
wants to defend psychology and considers
it to be so damn important and central
to our thinking they always quote other
Americans which just proves my point
that psychology is really a science
social science built on Cartesian
individualism and that is its problem no
you don't have to start the single human
being and then add another human being
and then you have three and four people
and finally have a tribe
no the tribe is where you start all
right I would I would claim a one-liner
head that maybe I could become you know
attributed to that one that is when you
talk about human beings nothing is less
than 157 mm-hmm our starting point for
being human is the tribe individual the
individual was invented by decart in
1632 because there were people who sat
and read books around Europe and they
discovered the power that they felt when
they read books and had their own
relationship to God and the world and
all that it enables us to create
Protestantism would never happen without
the printing press but it also enables
us to create a secular religion called
individuals and America was built on
individuals so entire American construct
is one that we are not really unified at
all except that will wave a flag there
are all individuals
so it's kind of a sort of weird union
between 300 million individuals that's
the ID of the United States murder now
Americans don't seem to understand how
weird this is to the rest of the world
and our exceptional it is and actually
there's nothing to do with the history
of ideas anywhere else in the world
it's an started in Europe that's true
but except for maybe England the rest of
you didn't care too much about
individualism and started problematizing
it pretty early and we reached the
French Revolution we got was so and this
bullshit going on certainly not
individuals didn't longer but then we
certainly got Marx who speaks about the
classes and class war and you know we
got Hegel's he talks about the system
and the absolute and the nation-states
and all these great thinkers in Europe
that we don't care too much about
individualism and the striking example
is when Freud the old Ford came to
America and he got very popular in
America he was another one of these
eccentric European intellectuals that
Americans like to import now and then
and he was imported to America but he
just he just found it disgusting because
the Freudians in America hadn't really
understood Freud at all they'd found his
psychoanalytical teachings into nothing
but American ego psychology I'm Sophie
because I college is the most American
thing that I could possibly think of so
this obsession with me being me alone in
Subsection with consciousness like
subjective experience and things like
that to me those things are actually
quite marginal to human beings in
general to the history of ideas to
anybody who recognizes that I'm a human
being I'm a flock animal I'm a social
creature 99% of the ideas that go
through my head are actually ideas have
gotten from other people I might have a
tiny little effect on those ideas before
I pass them on to somebody else
that's called medics but really you know
I'm just I'm just been where things are
thrown in and things start thrown out
and I try to make sense of the world and
when I really look at myself I
discovered that my sub consciousness
dictates way more of my behavior than my
consciousness ever does we are literally
not very conscious of anything that
happens to us yeah and they're making
consciousness
simple thing like it's you know easy so
central is one of the major narratives
or what it means to be human is today I
think a very American idea that
Europeans have given up on also
realizing the rest of the world didn't
really care
it's funny how also they instrumentalize
things like Buddhism for that right yeah
Western Buddhism has very little to do
with Buddhism because it has everything
to do with American ego psychology and
it seems to be like Americans cannot
import anything unless they're allowed
to take the filter ego psychology and
put up and then filter Eagle psychology
through that's exactly why when we talk
about people we love like Camille Paglia
Jordan Peterson John for Viking the
North Americans you and I love the most
they always have a problem with this
guide Lacan Chaka Khan and I I'm
beginning to understand the gut Lacan
perfected psychoanalysis
he took the heritage from Freud a young
and perfected it it's really hard once
you get into Meccano psychoanalysis to
get out of the trap that he puts you and
for him subjectivity is nothing but
emptiness it's just an empty hole the
tricks into doing all kinds of things or
tricks into believing kinds of things
but in a reality your body and your
subconsciousness have already decided
for you just about everything you do and
modern neuroscience proves that this
even is the case which is now really
screwing it up for the psychologists who
all don't believe it self awareness and
consciousness was so important and
they've been sitting there meditating
waiting to have some kind of empty
consciousness which to me is just
ridiculous why why is that important I
don't care well to get rid of your big
American fat ego maybe that's a good
idea for the rest of humanity we're
probably already as soon as we start you
know contemplating about the surrounding
world it's more like okay how am I gonna
look gonna get along with other people
today I'm gonna have some relationships
around me so I don't have to feel lonely
you have a team of people that I can
build amazing things together with you
know can I contribute to society those
are the things that human beings in
general find more important and none of
them has anything to do with this sort
of American Broadway mentality
you make it here you make it everywhere
you know which is ego psychology is most
extreme form so this is the problem with
session maybe right self-obsession
narcissism hello and it hasn't helped
that we got the Internet and the
internet was basically a very American
phenomenon hospital these don't tell no
influencers and everything we got today
the first 25 30 years of the Internet
has been an obsession with yourself
until people are gradually discovering
that there's nothing more boring than a
narcissist who writes newsletters about
himself that is very American woohoo
it's very American right we're tired of
it we're sick of it we're discovering it
doesn't work well maybe individualism in
itself never worked maybe was a bad idea
to begin with and it all led into these
silly ideas that we're all competing you
one another
and a life is some kind of competition
between individuals the most absurd form
of it all is of course I'm runs ideal
objectivism you know it was I mean
they're two massive ways of
misunderstanding freidy's Nietzsche one
of them is called out of Hitler and the
other one is called I am run and I
seriously haven't made up my mind yet on
who of the tube misunderstood servitor
worse yeah cuz both equally bad
philosophically speaking so no no
there's no objectivism ever in meetcha
meetcha meetcha understood how lonely we
are they understood the content and the
revolution you understood how the
categories are cursing us and that we
have to think through the categories to
understand the outside world and each is
still dreamed it's still dreamed of you
know the individual he's Cartesian
decides he dreamed individual who could
set himself free from the illusions of
reality and claim to himself his own
values this is the niche in here and in
this sense leadership fulfills the
Cartesian individualism you know yes it
is this is Nietzsche's problem now what
Peterson
table and threat them all down and their
own engines is that they go back to
nature and they tally with nature and
call it the meaning crisis it was maybe
a very latest literary philosophical
thing in the 19th century it's now a
mass phenomenon yeah we've all become
mediums right but the response to stay
with nature is the incorrect one what I
wanted to do in my work is to see me
choose my hero too and then kill him
my patricide is going to be the killing
of nature because we have to move on
from Nietzsche to some deeper concept
and a deeper understanding of what it
means to view and I've got a name for it
mm-hmm what's the name here right you
know Cynthia zoom tool it will to live
with Schopenhauer's eyes I will to
welter intelligence you're gonna say
sadly well to little Schopenhauer will
to power us nature I will sir - Kristen
are working on it's a philosophy that we
call wills - intelligence we little wing
till against right yeah you know
philosophers have avoided because that
is the answer to the mean increased
intelligence well it does one thing you
don't have to be human any longer to
talk about intelligence or have to be
humanistic and save the human race
mm-hmm it's not a humanistic project no
and Nietzsche was adamant he was an anti
humanist he despised the unist he saw no
reason out to be humanists for the same
reason you've been talking about with
this American sort of self obsession and
anthropocentrism self-consciousness fear
of having a greater vision that sort of
thing yeah and you have you have a
couple of things we should name here we
have of course
Daedelus who besides Lacan is the
greatest of the French thinkers of the
20th century and amazing I'm using the
lerz a lot we started with the less when
using with us in our next book written
to us all the time and I've got an old
brother of mine we talked about him
before that's Manuel de Landa and I
would I would really put in the work for
my little llama he's probably the best
of all the North America
contemporary philosophers monologue has
been a professor of architecture
Princeton for years he's a really
interesting thinker he doesn't get it
all right all the time because he's
lacking actually in the department of
American philosophy the two things I
lack in jolanda's work is he hasn't
studied Charles Saunders purse the
greatest American ever and he hasn't
started Whitehead the greatest British
thinker ever who who by the way it was
of course a philosopher in America in
their late century purse and whited or
America's two greatest contributions to
the philosophical pantheon Madeleine has
the potential to be the third the census
avoided person Whitehead and gone
straight for the European monastic think
resisted like Spinoza in dollars he's
lacking in that department because
there's a lot to learn from person white
as well especially about being
consequential we process whited open up
the door for quantum physics without
Whitehead would never have Niels Bohr
whenever I quantum physics so to
understand fully what process really is
to understand the primary aspect of time
over space what that means I don't see
any of this in jolanda's work at least
so far but the lamda is that a great job
at bringing dollars to America and every
time you you walk by a skyscraper that
has a rooftop garden on top of the
skyscraper you see what we call
D'Alessio architecture the ideal
blending Green straight into the urban
world for trees everywhere in the city
and all that that's all the lesson
thinking the land would claim so to so
they learned is a guide to read and
check out my mother London remember him
we're old friends and you know we were
sitting on skyscrapers in New York in
the nineteen eighties dream not being
philosophers one day we both became
philosophers the learner so friend
definitely worth checking out and
there's something interesting here
because the London office is not aware
of a table Peterson for America doing in
mass educating most education young
people today who understand we live in
the middle of a meaning crisis okay so
they're dealing with that and we embrace
that but de Landa is actually on the
other side already in that he actually
sits on the answers
knowing it we have to figure out a way
of uniting these two different streams
in American thinking so Montelongo and
aside needs to be more Imperial and be
more in work he's written a brilliant
book called the thousand years of
nonlinear history which is fantastic
imagine you rewrite the last 1000 years
of history from the perspective of virus
and bacteria and ignore human beings
mm-hmm then the plague was a great
golden age why not so the lander is
trained in thinking anti-humanist then
you might like the lasted you become a
right listen you focus on life that's a
first step life in itself becomes
important there's quite a few ecologists
and Eckhart Opium's as we call ourselves
now out there who think life is maybe
more important than human life so life
in general can be more important than
you love they they risk running into
problems like I want to keep the white
rhino and kill a human being to save the
white right now okay they have us to
hysterical problems they might have to
solve but you couldn't go for life I
would say why stay at life because we
look into it life really is a life form
as a separate cell cannot exist without
two things it needs a membrane a way to
communicate with the outside world where
it can differentiate between act can
differentiate between things that are
beneficial to it and things that are
dangerous to it so it has to it has to
learn to communicate with outside world
and let in that which is beneficial and
throw out that which is dangerous and
keep danger out right that kind of
membrane is the model for anything human
beings don't build you know if you build
a town you put you know a wall around it
to protect you from the outside world
that's a membrane hopefully not just a
stupid wall a memory you let things in
let things out to survive that's how a
cell orbit but that requires that the
membrane can remember
all previous transactions so you can't
remember that okay that was beneficial
to me yesterday I'll do more of that
that I thought was beneficial yes they
turned out to be dangerous I will not
repeat that mistake that I thought was
dangerous yesterday but I should have
known it was beneficial so I give it
another try that was literal dangerous
good now remember these things so I know
right so you your on and off switches
that requires memory so this this can i
this could I just have an intuition that
you're talking about artificial
intelligence in some sense no no I'm
still talking about logical intelligence
I know but but but wooden wouldn't that
be the proper use for artificial
intelligence no okay
well I'll explain what this is a memory
separate this is how memories need
memory and as soon as your membrane in a
memory you have life that means
biological intelligence and life are the
same thing okay there is no life that is
a stupid son attendant that means
biological intelligence is also
emotional intelligence mm-hmm they are
the same thing that means if you talk
about world to intelligence you can
remove shopping hours will to live and
it's redundant you've already embraced
life then the next question is meet your
dreams about worlds to power like I want
to expand and you know grow grow grow
well that only what happens with a life
form when it runs into competition
without life or so say you got you got a
certain set of resources in a certain
area and suddenly you've got a lot of
thriving life forms in that area
and it certainly some of those life
forms are dying because there's not
enough nutrition for everybody that then
looks like it's able to power because
the only life forms to it exist are the
ones that somehow have figured out are
the use their intelligence to expand
mm-hmm Darwin you know Darwinian exactly
then you get dog okay you get John but
the thing is this when Nietzsche wants
to make rules to power some kind of
ethical principle he's wrong no that's
just a byproduct for Darwinian evolution
there's nothing more tune so
intelligence though can you go back and
see
Walter power is nothing but a byproduct
of Darwinian evolution okay
remember the static list and I are
siding with Darby against nature darling
we are more divinium than Darwin himself
whereas Nietzsche hasn't set he has a
limit how far you can go with Nietzsche
he completes the Cartesian Revolution
but he ends up as the last and biggest
proponent of Western individualism and
that is his response to Christianity and
he will also fail there's a Christianity
failed and had his death born into it
from the very beginning
individualism had its own death
Mornington from the very beginning and
that's when division was dying and each
just means that's interesting that's
like Nietzsche is the death of
Christianity in a way well he's the last
he's the last Cartesian to be honest on
that mm-hmm so we'll finish them with
cartesianism and Nietzsche and we'll we
look at them as wilt intelligence and
then we can look at okay so we created
machine intelligence great
now it's machine intelligence similar to
biological Intel is though not at all
that's wonderful because then we can
work towards something
Daanish miltenberger we should credit
him for that has already called
symbiotic intelligence there's no
conflict between man and machine
intelligence in itself is not evil
because intelligence in itself strives
to check if it can unify itself with
other intelligences two cells would try
to find out what if we unify and become
a larger cell that's why we so easily
merge with technology yeah exactly and
the great thing of a scene in China is
while we take two it is precisely
because it does not mimic human
intelligence human intelligence should
be understood as biological intelligence
and starting from plants and moving on
to animals we get higher and higher
complexities they can handle more and
more information and of course animals
to our life forms that can store and
memorize things in their memory and the
memory teaches them to do certain things
again and again and to not do certain
things that again and
new things okay so that is how we learn
all the time okay dogs learn horses
learn it's so human intelligence those
human intelligence can you help me
understand machine intelligence like cuz
you know clothing right technology and I
are starting from the beginning and then
now there's now there's I'm not able to
crave life okay so even if we're gonna
do synthetic biology and it's gonna be
huge to the center we're still going to
use life form store it exists and then
tame them investigate them so synthetic
biology is gonna be the next level of
domestication the human domestication
that you know I love genetically
modified foods that's why I make Autopia
not environmentalist
I love nuclear power by the way - I love
technologies that actually enhance human
life and if technologies can give us
better cheaper food and if acknowledges
a more sustained some more sustainable
waste without putting pesticides out
there and if technology can give us more
abundant cheap energy all for the better
okay that's from Innokin opium not
environmentalist but but when we go to
machine intelligence the advantage to
machine intelligence is actually
incredibly stupid but it's incredibly
fast reliable it's the speed and the
reliability of computers that makes yeah
I've got another costume jump in my mind
when you said that I think in saying
this is like slavery right yeah yeah it
finally we have happy slaves happy
slaves right and because stopping
hypocrites about slavery
human beings love sleep because we are
lazy bastards and we love somebody to
jerk off our dicks and you know all
kinds of things well obviously right so
we had slaves before and then we fooled
ourselves into believing we've become
good human beings slavery longer it was
just basically that we got rid of
slavery because why pay for somebody 24
hours a day where you can pay for their
upkeep when we eat hours a day and then
you call it work yeah now we don't even
have that cost you know a lot of workers
were done then whatever we're gonna
invent a lot of new really cheap service
jobs for people so that will keep them
missing you know give them some kind of
money they can spend universal basic
income it's never going to happen what's
gonna
the service sectors expanding expand
like they've done in America we're gonna
see the same thing of the rest of world
you're all gonna have jobs in the future
but they're probably gonna be cheap jobs
and poorly paid okay but you gonna have
jobs right but slaves good slaves to
work hard 24 hours a day
never bitch and complain are called
computers no no the machines will be our
slaves and here comes the most important
thing what will be the number one thing
we need to tell the machines what is the
biggest dream we have today to save
ourselves and save this planet for human
life we have to distinguish between the
Machine intelligence and human
intelligence right talked about it I
said it started in Persia three thousand
seven hundred years ago and the Jews
carpeted for themselves which is the
biggest story of them all okay we need a
damn Savior okay what is the best
mission we could possibly give a machine
that's so the machine is going to be the
Messiah sort of things that means one
messianic storytelling is so important
and that is where I'm moving with
service next and the completion of our
trilogy hopefully in the next three
years that's so kind of like the
opposite of what everybody's thinking
that's so that's so interesting it's the
total opposite of this dystopian story
that everybody is telling well grateful
to hear that well we're down in flames
and but they're you know when you speak
when you say messianic it's it's always
a gamble and it's always gonna involved
a few people that's what's called an
exodus the few people actually add her
to a message and actually take it
seriously and most people will not but
the people who will will create some
kind of an exodus into the digital
vertical world we're moving into and
they're gonna take this idea with them
that by creating a community people who
devoted to the cause of creating the
Messianic machine now there
you go that that is the biggest story of
our time we've been pointing towards
insider Kristen over the last few years
we wrote the Sun for some book to
basically the framework for it and say
religion everything is religion you know
individualism is just bad religion
Christianity is just dead religion but
it's still religion okay how do you
create a living religion that you
actually believe in that will get people
moving in the right direction finally
and understand there's something more
meaningful that's about to happen and
could happen even in their own lifetime
well then came to this a little bit up
with just a warning second book of the
Prophet SAW is the one he says that if
you don't add hair to the story we're
about to tell you you're gonna go down
in flames so the next 50 years conflicts
our culture wars are a perfect example
of that number the culture wars have
even hit burning man in the Kapadia
we're in deep trouble
there's not a single space left in
American or English society today that
isn't infected with the culture war and
it's devastating it's devastating it's a
plague of ugliness or something right
it is absolutely and and I'm worried
about it I've said all along if you
ignore Charlottesville's you do it at
your own peril Portland Oregon today
literally is a work out between these
two cats Charlottesville hasn't moved to
Portland Oregon and it now has a
permanent address yeah these guys are
now building bombs and that's where
antifa and that's what they all try
they're gonna throw the bombs at each
other for the first time and they're
gonna love it
cuz they love asket ology they love to
go down a fence there's this this
inherent nature to human beings that
they love warfare and they love
apocalypse and love this ecology in the
long term you know they're waiting for
the rapture of some kind or anything
Wow or to die as hero just we need to
come up but this is not a third
alternative I am NOT saying we created
the synthesis or way out of a dilemma
like childhood because then we just
bring us back into the old corrupt
society we have to leave behind mm-hmm I
hate the institutions today I despise
politics
I despise academia I despise the
corporate sector
I despise all the guys out there who are
the old institutions or the old power
structures and do nothing else to try to
defend their privileges that's why we
have this sort of deep a popular
uprising against Washington DC now
they're going after Silicon Valley next
and Silicon Valley is just a bunch of
nerds that are defenseless that's
exactly why I want to get out of the
tech giants as quickly as possible I
want a life that's dependent of Google
or Facebook or any of these companies
any longer because they're so damn
vulnerable now they have no principles
they don't stand for anything and as
soon as there is an attack somewhere out
in the media did they try to follow that
and try to please everybody now people
who try to please everybody and kiss
your ass all the time never trust it
that means you cannot trust the tech
giants in Silicon Valley at all that's
why smart people at PETA theum their
advice and all those guys are getting
out so you're getting out of there we
need to create something new
Domenic Tarn scuttlebutt and these guys
are those of my friends that I'm most
impressed with at the moment these guys
to try to create new flat technological
structures that cannot really be damaged
by say the culture wars at all these are
systems that are immune to the culture
wars and they're new to the old
institutions that means political
institutions academic institutions the
central banks of the world the corporate
sector cannot even filtration these are
the new sort of anarchic or libertarian
heroes out there the serta Kristen I
have predicted will lead the way to the
Exodus so it's within these communities
you find the people they're gonna be the
winners the real heroes they don't make
money today
they don't do tech startups that's just
the first way over than autocracy no no
you're coming as the third way way later
become as the third way to take to to
take benefit all with the internet
Trulia's right on it in an honest
radically honest way understanding that
you have to be radical on this to
survive trust the algorithms as they
point the way forward and way the
algorithms you have the
Exodus towards the Messianic machine hmm
you have to be radically honest to
survive that's that's interesting uh
well it's all based on intelligence its
intelligence and you look at machine
intelligence BI and MRI come on up
called symbiotic intelligence symbiotic
intelligence of a man a machine both
work together after optimal so create
any system that involves the best of
human capacity and the best of machine
capacity and they collaborate together
to create the largest possible output
that's symbiotic internal justice si I
never used the term artificial
intelligence you've been throwing up
right away it's totally not interesting
miss it's a misnomer
so symbiotic intelligence is the way
forward the question is then what is
symbiotic intelligence we're at pure
clean I'm almost sounding moralistic in
a pure and clean ethical algorithm will
be keep a nervous algorithm that is
prone to change depending on how
politics is changing or how media is
changing or or an algorithm that can be
infiltrated by social lynch mobs like
Google searches today terrible but we
can create deeply honest algorithms only
block chains to do it the race of my
Burning Man and Wikipedia are also no
falling to the culture wars because
they're not watching anything that's
blocked chained cannot be changed and
then it cannot be altered by lynch mobs
it cannot be altered by the moods of the
day with the fads of the day and that's
the only thing we can trust the future
is the algorithm that is immune to fans
confessions that locks in history at any
given point in time and says this is
what actually happened because this is
the next thing because that algorithm
will be so brutally honest that will
open up humanity to brutal honesty
between each other and that is the only
way for any trader worked along the
trade route knew that if he wanted to do
deal with somebody from a different clan
than his own which is what he did all
the time you had to go to the bathhouse
in the afternoon
and whorehouse and evening before he
could trust the other guy so they were
naked together and it could trust in the
next day insanity everything since then
has been about trust and Trust can only
occur when there's transparency the only
way you trust another person by seeing
straight people being naked together
metaphorically speaking
that is what algorithms can do you can
do why do you think you have an
obsession with blockchains
and contracts because contracts is the
fundament of what civilization Essaouira
asterism describes it is precisely by
writing a contract signing contracts
this property is yours and this property
mine so you can invest in your property
I can invest in my property and then we
can trade with each other we both
benefit from the gains we thereby made
that is the basis of civilization and to
me now the culture wars are killing
absolutely everything that is just a
reminder that the next time you create
something like a pinata we have to
create it with the blockchain algorithm
so that it's totally immune to the
hysterical lynch mob shelter because
anything that is affected by this
terrible lynch mob south about there was
so anism of the day he's gonna go down
in flames
mm-hm Portland Oregon being you know the
evidence of that hmm we need to create
something way more stable than that and
stability is phallus and to do that
we've come up with another concept I'm
glad to present and we call it the root
of the fellas okay the way the root of
the palace the root of the fathom the
bottom of the farm through the rich
shock reviews corny terrible okay
root chakra so that's that's a good
chance it's a take that from Buddhism
then in Orland for it and say root of
the fellows okay this Orestes talk my
promise all the time
so does Freud but they never actually
discuss the far as a detail okay well
the phallus has details okay when you
build the skyscraper
what is the most important thing you
have to do and they just spend 90% of
your time in doom join the architects
the preliminaries to the basement
basement the basement okay what do you
do today to build a fantastic position
like the what we're working on here with
a Missoni machine and everything how do
you build that how do you come to these
conclusions how do you come up with
these ideas you go deeper down into
history mm-hmm probably for vacant for
record by the way anybody out there
we wanna you know fill the gaps in the
holes in your conception of history
young for vodka is the best damn You
Tube teacher you're ever going to find
and teach you thinking over the past
3,000 years there it's underrated but
you go before that and then you come of
course to the original tribe and the
original tribe started about two hundred
thousand years ago with the first Homo
sapiens in Africa and then it moved on
until about five thousand years ago and
civilization occurred and during that
period 195,000 years all our genes were
created meaning we are still
sociological meaning we are still cycle
yeah we're still the same people that is
something that Peterson and partly uh
and in correct it never discuss and the
reason why they don't reach to the
Messiah ideas is because they haven't
gone deep enough into history so if you
go deeper down interest rate to the root
of the fellows you go back five or ten
thousand years and then you go about 150
thousand years and you get the whole
genetic makeup and understand what human
beings work the way they do you get the
archetypes you understand why people are
different
you understand why everybody in the
society has some kind of role you
understand different men and women and
you understand their drug you're those
people you get the full tribal now the
only way to do that is go deeper now
mister we can call a deep history if you
like but deepest your winger they're
moving to philosophy you're gonna create
something into the future becomes the
ruinous house because you want it you
want to aim high okay so the new the
deeper the you go the higher you can aim
in other words exactly
okay so we got will to intelligence
which is more Buddhist in the system
will to intelligence operates like you
think of cells
membranes of life-forms in Berlin next
to each other and they sort of touch
each other and they go intertwine with
each other and then they sort of
separate and then they go back in and
you know you look you look at a
microscope is he life is bursty that
never happens in computers
okay we just aren't off on off on off so
the total opposite of computers but
that's about nautical intelligence
operates right that is kind of flat
structures whereas we dream vertically
which founded structure
so so you could say that live for
intelligence in itself it's kind of a
Buddhist thing but once you add well to
it and you talk a wolf to intelligence
which like we want to get somewhere you
become a sir Esther because you then say
no to the Buddhist ambition of killing
your desires and if I hadn't found what
I believe gives my life meaning which is
the messianic story I'm talking about
here and I want to complete this as
philosopher if hadn't found that that
I've become totally impossible if the
meaning Christ is read and arrived at a
point where they could not be in the
meaning again and religion cannot be
recreated I would gladly become a
Buddhist I think it's a I think it's a
very sound response to Buddhism doesn't
have this prophetic quality there that's
why fabric is a Buddhist mm-hmm okay hi
to respect that choice David makes much
more sense than being so kind of ironic
Christian which is where Peters in rival
well he's kind of an ironic Buddhist
actually I have a slight problem with
his Buddhism but phonetic East Buddhism
he has some things Stephen Bachelor you
know Stephen Bachelor wrote this book
called Buddhism with that beliefs yeah I
think is ridiculous to have her because
you can't have nowadays a belief to say
Buddhism whether please like I believe
there's a Buddhism with them it's like
it's like it's like this Buddhism that
can be whatever it's it's I think he
wants to become sort of a post bonus
Buddhist but he won't he won't take on
the whole sounds very silly try not
pretty Tantra so I'm a yeah going up to
my
if you check Buddhism you only do half
of it that's that's for certain
right you both an are into Tantra stuff
yeah and mantra is of course
Sandra's the surface against which
sorceress and fits and we do nism you
cannot understand why so asters and
complements Buddhism unless you first
become attentive Buddhist
mm-hm because tantric is the phallic
aspect of Buddhism where a Sutra
dominates Buddhism why at least why
called the magical religion you could
say that well you I could as a Buddhist
take on any of the Saurashtra beliefs
yes you could if you could become an
empty Buddhist the problem is you still
fighting religion the claims that the
extinction of desire is the element God
no it isn't death is not the goal this
is just the endpoint of the narrative
mm-hmm the meaning is actually to
protest against death live as long as
you can live the holdest fullest logic
possibly crap and then accept death
because if you hadn't accepted death
life will be horrible that is the surah
astron take on life in death
so we are born we know we're gonna die
we know life is meaningless unless we
create meaning in it we know it could
just prolong our lives in a sort of
meaningless existence what we're too
scared to even kill ourselves and that's
the Monty know you could live like that
in Freud says unfortunately most human
beings have no more self-confidence than
that in this state in the Moutinho most
of us and then never even show any kind
of libido libido is vain protest against
that it's like yeah we're a dick you
don't want to make things so nobody
create things and all build skyscrapers
I don't want to be the messiah or have
the Messiah come and create something
wonderful than amazing what that desire
might be ultimately vain because you're
gonna die one name but that's just
that's just a truism which is absolutely
obvious no because when you die you pass
on the world to the next generation
mm-hmm that's how the world's provides
yeah that's how you prolong life that
that is that is adding value to life
that goes beyond your grave you create
something for others to take up and do
something with before you die
that's called heritage it has a deep
deep human teaser and I would say
heritage could be also an aspect of will
to intelligence heritage but we have to
look at the actual arguments for that
before we actually claim something like
that maybe some of the followers we have
here are friends of ours that are
following us could add to that
discussion could heritage mean aspect of
world's intelligence well you know when
does a life-form become so intelligent
you realize he's gonna die one day and
that fact is gonna die one day
it's actually an escape of some kind and
because that's an escape and value can
be added to what happens before that
escape occurs mm-hmm like teaching or
something
well I think language certainly made it
possible for us as human beings to
understand we're gonna die one day and
that's of course both both both the
cursing of us but that's what we're
always dealing with formica talks about
peters and talks america talks about
anybody's talking about the meaning
crisis right now constantly talk about
the fact that human beings know they're
gonna die one day and they cannot
comprehend what is fine
you can comprehend that other people are
dying but you come with comprehend the
yoga which is the according to mark on
is the one little thing you save for
yourself to not exploit factors yourself
as an illusion the last thing you say in
of yourself in your in your sense of
self to not have to deal with the fact
of yourself a solution is the fact you
save it by not being able to comprehend
that it can go away